Guide to the Herman F. Mark Collection RG.002
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Herman F. Mark Collection
1918-2013
1928-1992
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
RG.002
4
50 Linear Feet (30 boxes)
The Herman Mark Collection documents the personal and profession life of Herman Francis Mark, the Father of Polymer Science. During his fifty years at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, Mark developed the field of polymer science in the United States, published over 600 articles, and founded the Institute of Polymer Research, the first graduate program of its kind in America.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eleven series, by subject:
This collection is arranged into eleven series, by subject:
List
Personal and Biographical
Correspondence
Writings
Publications
Subject Files
Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn and the Polymer Research Institute
Photographs
Framed Photographs and Documents
Magnetic Media
Personal Items and Miscellaneous
Collection Provenance and Information
Scope and Contents
The collection contains professional and personal items of Herman Mark, including publications, pre-prints and drafts, notes, photographs, slides, awards, correspondence, festschrift, government documents, professional contacts, audio and video tapes. The VHS and U-matic tapes were digitized in 2013 and are stored on a local server.
The bulk of the collection relates to Mark's tenure at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (1940-1990), although some documents and photographs detail his early years in Vienna and his final years in Texas. Mark was a beloved figure at Polytechnic and beyond, as documented by his Polytechnic birthday symposia celebrations and birthday wishes from around the world.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Biographical / Historical
Herman Francis Mark, The Father of Polymer Science, was born in Vienna on May 3, 1895. Although his schooling was interrupted by World War I, in which he served on the front lines as well as spending a year as a prisoner of war, he managed to complete his doctoral dissertation on the synthesis and characterization of the pentaphenyl ethyl free radical. His doctoral advisor, Wilhelm Schlenk, subsequently offered Mark a position at the University of Berlin in 1921.
Mark's position at the university had barely begun when he was offered a job at the Institute for Fiber Research at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute. Here he worked on projects including x-ray crystallographic, refraction, and polarization studies. In 1926 he took a position at I.G. Farbenindustrie to study the production of synthetic fibers. At the start of World War II, he sought employment outside of Germany, becoming a professor of chemistry at the University of Vienna in 1932. There he designed a curriculum in polymer chemistry.
With the Nazi threat looming, Mark and his family prepared to escape Europe by covertly buying bits of platinum wire and twisting it into coat hangers in order to accumulate money for travel and a new life. By the time the Mark family escaped to Canada, they had amassed $50,000 in platinum wire.
Herman Mark joined the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (PIB) as an adjunct professor in 1940. Mark's position at PIB, as well as his relationships with DuPont and the wartime Office of Scientific Research and Development, led to further developments in polymer research. In 1947, the Institute of Polymer Research was founded at PIB; the first graduate program of its kind in America. Mark continued his relationship with PIB for over 50 years. He died in 1992.
The discipline of polymer science that Mark helped to establish is now a vital branch of chemistry. Polymers, macromolecules formed synthetically by uniting monomers, have high viscosity, elasticity, and strength. The first synthetic fiber, nylon, was a result of Mark's work in polymers. Today many scientific companies conduct polymer research.
Sources:
"Herman Francis Mark" nap.edu. The National Academies Press Biographical Memoirs. n.d. Web. 29 Aug. 2012.
Rodengen, Jeffrey L, and Mickey Murphy. Changing the World: Polytechnic University - - the First 150 Years. Fort Lauderdale, FL: Write Stuff Enterprises, Inc, 2005. Print.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Hans Mark in 2016.
Audio-visual materials; Correspondence; Clippings; Brochures; Articles; Photographs; Photography negatives; Lecture notes; Monographs; Speeches; Videotapes; Polymer engineering; Reprints; Polymer Research Institute. Polytechnic University (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Mark, Hans; Immergut, E. H. (Edmund H.); Atlas, Sheldon M.; Mark, Herman F. (Herman Francis); Pearce, Eli M.; Overberger, Charles Gilbert, Dr.; Katzir, Ephraim; Braunsteiner, E.E. (Elfi); Eirich, F. R. (Frederick Roland); Morawetz, Herbert; Weber, Ernst; Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn; Polytechnic Institute of New York; Polytechnic University (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bugliarello, George (Georgio Bugliarello-Wondrich); Koch, Ed; Lord Corporation; Goodman, Murray
- Series I: Biographical, 6449
  - Subseries A: Biographical sketches and essays, 6450
    - Herman F. Mark biographical outline, undated; 9366 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographical Sketch- Herman Francis Mark, undated; 9367 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Autobiography, undated; 9368 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Autobiography (with D.O. Hummel and H. Tschamler), undated; 9654 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Biography (through retirement), undated; 9369 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Biography (including post-retirement) and publication lists, undated; 9370 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Biography- Herman Francis Mark, undated; 9371 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Biography- Herman Francis Mark (bound), undated; 9372 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Herman F. Mark- Polymer Pioneer, undated; 9373 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Polymer Science Pioneers, undated; 9374 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Untitled Biography, undated; 9375 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Short Biography (in German), undated; 9376 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Subseries B: Passports and personal documents, 6454
    - Herman Mark Republic of Baden driver's license and Austrian National committee card, 1927, 1942; 9377 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Herman Mark Austrian passports, 1936, 1938; 9378 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Herman Mark German passport, 1939; 9379 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Herman Mark United States passports, 1962, 1981; 9380 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Canadian Immigration Cards- Herman, Maria, Peter, and Hans Mark, 1938; 9381 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Maria Mark German and Austrian passports, 1938, 1939; 9382 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Maria Mark United States passports, 1959, 1963; 9383 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Peter Mark United Stated passports, 1949, 1953; 9384 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Herman Mark notarized copies of birth date, place, parents, marriage status, and American citizenship (in German), 1987, 1991; 9385 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Herman Mark marriage status document, 1992; 9386 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Maria Mark death certificate (copy), 1970 March 10; 9387 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Herman Mark death certificate and correspondence, 1992; 9388 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Herman Mark membership cards, 1990; 9389 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Mark family birth dates and anniversaries, undated; 9390 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Subseries C: Awards and Honors, 9013
    - Medals, Awards, and Honors lists, undated; 9391 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Awards and Recognition, 1966-1991; 9392 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Special Merits in the Area of Plastics medal, 1975; 9393 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Mayor's Award of Honor for Science and Techology, 1986; 9394 (Box 1, Item 1)
    - Mark Bust Dedication program and sculptor's resume, 1959, 2013; 9395 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Introduction of Dr. Mark for Commencement, 1965 June 9; 9396 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Honorary doctorate from the University of Vienna, 1980; 9679 (Box 30, Item 2)
    - Weizmann Institute of Science, Herman Mark Chair (scroll in tube), 1986; 9717 (Box 30, Item 3)
  - Subseries D: Tributes, 9012
    - "Citation" Herman Francis Mark, undated; 9397 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "Herman Mark's Children" by N. Bikales, undated; 9398 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "Shared Passages" by H. Wechsler, 1992; 9399 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "A Tribute to Herman Mark, Mr. Polymer Science" by. M. Goodman, undated; 9400 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Herman Mark: Life and Accomplishments" by. H. Morawetz, 1995; 9401 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "Our Debt to Polymer Pioneers" by E. Jefferson, 1980 June 11; 9402 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Herman Mark, the man: The chemist as perceived by his son and others" by Hans Mark, 1982 January; 9403 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "Herman Mark- A Legend in his Lifetime" by H. Morawetz, undated; 9404 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Subseries E: Obituaries, 6455
    - Obituaries- clippings and photocopies, 1992; 9405 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Obituraries- long form, 1992; 9406 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Subseries F: Interviews and oral histories, 6451
    - Herman Mark Interview, 1965; 9407 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Herman Mark Interview with Alan Stahl, 1979; 9408 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Chemical Heritage Foundation oral history abstracts, 2003; 9409 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Center for the History of Chemistry transcript of interview at Poly (bound), 1986 February 3; 9410 (Box 1, Item 2)
    - Herman Mark Oral History- National Foundation for History of Chemistry (bound), 1986; 9411 (Box 1, Item 3)
    - The Beckman Center for the History of Chemistry: Herman Mark, transcript of interviews conducted by J. Bohning and J. Sturchuo at Polytechnic University (binder), 1986; 9412 (Box 1, Item 4)
  - Subseries G: Professional contacts, 6453
    - Sponsors and Contacts, undated; 9413 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Contacts A-F (index cards), undated; 9414 (Box 2)
    - Contacts G-L (index cards), undated; 9415 (Box 3)
    - Contacts M-Se (index cards), undated; 9416 (Box 4)
    - Contacts Sh-Z and additional sets (index cards), undated; 9417 (Box 5)
- Series II: Correspondence, 6456
  - Subseries A: Personal, 6457
    - Maria Mark Condolences, 1970; 9673 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1970, 1970 July-September; 9418 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1970, 1970 August; 9419 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1970, 1970 September; 9420 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner (and business card), 1970, 1970 October; 9421 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner to M.A. Siddique, 1970, 1970 November 27; 9422 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1970, 1970 November; 9423 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner (with clippings), 1970-1971, 1970 December - 1971 January; 9424 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1971, 1971 January; 9425 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1971, 1971 February - May; 9426 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1971, 1971 March - June; 9427 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner (with photographs), 1971, 1971 June; 9428 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner (with clippings), 1971, 1971 September - November; 9429 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1972, 1972 January - March; 9430 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1972, 1972 April - May; 9431 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1972, 1972 September - December; 9432 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1972, 1972 December 16; 9433 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1973, 1973 January - May; 9434 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1973, 1973 July; 9435 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1973, 1973 October - December; 9436 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Elfi Braunsteiner, 1970s, 9437 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Vicki, 1973 July 4; 9438 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous cards (with photographs, 1972-1984; 9439 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1980-1990; 9674 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Subseries B: Professional, 6458
    - U.S. Naval Ordnance Test Station, Inyokern (contains reports, contracts, Communist questionnaire), 1953 January - August; 9440 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Hermann Staudinger, 1961 October 25; 9441 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Ephraim Katchalski-Katzir, 1978 January 25; 9442 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - President Reagan, 1980; 9443 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - A. Kabil, 1980 April 28; 9444 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Kahane, 1980 April 28; 9445 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Mary Wisnovsky, 1981 June 19; 9446 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous professional correspondence, 1985; 9447 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - H. Schwager (re: Knischka Rubies), 1986; 9448 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Miscellaneous professional correspondence, 1987 February - November; 9449 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous professional correspondence, 1987 May; 9456 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - George Bugliarello, 1989 February 8; 9450 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Miscellaneous professional correspondence, 1990; 9451 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Pykrete Technology Group (contains report), 1990; 9452 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Greve Foundation, 1990; 9457 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Peter Brady, 1990; 9505 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Margaret Mastrianni, 1990 February 22; 9458 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - George Bugliarello, 1990 July 7; 9459 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous professional correspondence, 1990 October; 9460 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - A.S. Abhiraman (contains reports), 1990 November 28; 9453 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Re: Lectures, 1990; 9454 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Re: Lectures, 1991; 9455 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Sheldon Atlas (after Mark's death), 1992; 9461 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Gloria Fazio, 1992; 9464 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Chemical Heritage Foundation, 1997; 9462 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Miscellaneous, 1972-1991; 9463 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Personalized Polytechnic stationary and business cards, undated; 9465 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Blank stationary and cards, undated; 9466 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Blank postcard collection, undated; 9467 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Blank postcard collection, undated; 9468 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Mail from Bruce Ganetz February 27, 2018 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Subseries C: Mixed mail (collected by secretary, Gloria Fazio), 9014
    - Mail to GHR, 1981, 1981 February; 9677 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Mail to GHR, 1983, 1983 July; 9469 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Mail to GHR, 1985, 1985 November 1; 9470 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Mail to GHR, 1985, 1985 November 11; 9471 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Mail to GHR, 1986, 1986 February 24; 9472 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Mail to GHR, 1986, 1986 February - May; 9473 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Mail to GHR, 1986, 1986 May 13; 9474 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Mail to GHR, 1986, 1986 May 19; 9475 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Mail to GHR, 1986, 1986 May 27; 9476 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Mail to GHR, 1986, June 2, 1986; 9477 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, April 10, 1987; 9478 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 April 15; 9479 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 May 1; 9480 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 May 8; 9481 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 May 15; 9482 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 May 22; 9483 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 July 24; 9484 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 July 31; 9485 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 August 6; 9486 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 December 4; 9487 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 December 11; 9488 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Mail to GHR, 1987, 1987 December 21; 9489 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Mail to GHR, 1988, 1988 July 25; 9496 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Mail to GHR, 1988, 1988 August 15; 9497 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Mail to GHR, 1988, 1988 September 23; 9498 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 June 6; 9490 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 July 14; 9491 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 July 21; 9492 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 August 2; 9493 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 August 14; 9494 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 August 17; 9495 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 December 7; 9499 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Mail to GHR, 1989, 1989 December 19; 9500 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 March 9; 9501 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 April 3; 9502 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 April 6; 9503 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 April 12; 9504 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 June 29; 9506 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 July 6; 9507 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 July 17; 9508 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 July 27; 9509 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 August 3; 9510 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 August 13; 9511 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 August 22; 9512 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 September 6; 9513 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 September 13; 9514 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 September 19; 9515 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 September 26; 9516 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 October 2; 9517 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 October 18; 9518 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Mail to GHR, 1990, 1990 October 26; 9519 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Subseries D: Inter-Office Correspondence and memoranda, 6606
    - Inter-Office Correspondence, 1967, 9520 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Inter-Office Correspondence and memos (with information about Mark videos), 1968; 9521 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Memos, 1987; 9522 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Inter-Office Mail, 1991; 9523 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1981-1983; undated; 9524 (Box 7, Folder 40)
- Series III: Writings, 6459
  - Subseries A: Preprints, personal essays, drafts, 6460
    - 25 Years of Polymer Science in Brooklyn, undated; 6607 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - A Brief Report on the Development of Polymer Science and Engineering, undated; 8998 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Ad Memoriam of Guilio Natta, circa 1979; 9018 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Amerika Oder Oesterreich? [America or Austria?], undated; 9017 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Cellulose - Origin, Structure, Uses - A Personal Journey, undated; 6608 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Chemistry and Aviation, undated; 6609 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - China-Besuch, 1972 June; 9021 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Contemporary and Future Textile Science Engineering, undated; 6610 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Early Studies on Rubber Structure and Elasticity, undated; 6611 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Early Work on Electron Diffraction, undated; 9015 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Elastomers Past-Present-Future, undated; 6612 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Electro-and Photoresponsive Polymers, undated; 6613 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - From Revolution to Evolution, undated; 6614 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - From Small Organic Molecules to Large: A Century of Progress, undated; 6615 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Future Improvements of Cohesive and Adhesive Strength, undated; 6616 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Future Trends in Polymer Science and Technology, undated; 6617 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Goodyear's Discovery and Modern Elastomer Synthesis, undated; 6618 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Hermann Staudinger: Scientist, Educator, Pioneer, undated; 9002 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - History of Polymer Structure, undated; 6619 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Internal Polyolefines and a Few Highly Substituted Poly Vinyls, 1986 January 27; 8996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Man-Made Fibers - In the 1980's, undated; 6620 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Michelson-Morley, undated; 6621 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Modes for Synthetic Fiber Formation, undated; 6622 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - New Concepts -- New Polymers -- New Applications, undated; 9016 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - New Frontiers in Polymer Expansion, undated; 6624 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Optically Active Synthetic Polymers, undated; 6625 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Organic Polymers and the Environment, undated; 6626 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Organic Polymers with Exceptional Performance, undated; 6627 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Our Century is One of Polymer Science and Engineering, undated; 6628 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Plastics, undated; 6629 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Plastics-The Next 20 Years, undated; 6630 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Polyester Fibers, undated; 6631 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Polymer Science and Engineering: Facts and Trends, 1984 September; 8994 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Polymeric Materials: Natural and Synthetic, undated; 8995 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Polymers and Composites, undated; 6632 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Polymers From Now to the Year 2000, undated; 6633 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Polymers in the Last Hundred Years, undated; 6634 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Polymers in Material Science, undated; 9007 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Polymers in the Service of Man, undated; 9008 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Polymers to the Year 2000 - And Beyond - A Forecast, 1987; 6635 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Polymers of the 1980's, undated; 6636 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Polymers of the 1990's, undated; 6637 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Polyolefins -- What Next?, 9005 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Progress in Polymers- A Forecast, undated; 8997 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Proposal to Establish a Center of Polytechnic Biotechnology and Othmer Institute, undated; 9181 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Remembering the Early Days of Polymer Science, undated; 9003 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Report on Liquid-Solid Relations, 8999 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Report on Stereoregulated Polymerization, undated; 9004 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Report on the Use of Synthetic Polymers in Medical Sciences, 1981 December 15; 9000 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Seventy-Five Years of Polymer Science and Technology, undated; 6638 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Some Background for the Textile Industry in the 20th Century, undated; 9001 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Studies on the Rheology of Asphalt-Polyolefin Blends, undated; 6639 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Synthetic Fibers From Petrochemicals, undated; 6641 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Synthetic Polymers in Medical Sciences, 1976; 9006 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - The Natural Sciences in our Century, undated; 6642 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated; 9020 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous opinion and review, 1978-1981; 9883 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Subseries B: Speeches and Presentations, 6488
    - Patents relating to presentations, 1958-1973; 9135 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence regarding presentations, 1974 May 20; 9134 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - "For Slides", undated; 9136 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "For Slides" including "Organic Polymers and the Environment", undated; 9138 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "For Slides" including Advanced Composites Applications Model 767, undated; 9139 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - "For Slides" including Rubber, undated; 9525 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Springy Fibers, undated; 9140 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Properties of Springy Polypropylene Filaments, 1965-1967; 9141 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Fibers", undated; 9142 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Slides", undated; 9143 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Loose papers - fibers, elastomers, KCals, acrylics, Poly flow chart, undated; 9144 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Future Trends in Polymer Research- The Second W.H. Carothers Lecture, 1978 September; 9130 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Polymer Scientist slides, 1983; 9137 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - C.G. Overberger: Pioneer, Educator, Innovator, Administrator, Model, 1985; 9132 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Polymers of the 1980s: Familiar Concepts - New Vistas, undated; 9133 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - New Concepts - New Polymers - New Applications, undated; 6623 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Oversize lecture drawings, undated; 9019 (Box 10, Item 1)
- Series IV: Publications, 6464